<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Depeche Node</title>
    <link>https://deurell.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Depeche Node</description>
    <generator>Hugo - gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <contact>dev@deurell.net</contact>
    <copyright></copyright>
    
        <atom:link href="https://deurell.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching kids game development with PICO-8</title>
      <link>https://deurell.github.io/posts/crazy-comets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>Mikael Deurell</author>
      <guid>https://deurell.github.io/posts/crazy-comets/</guid>
      <description></description>
      
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Growing up I loved to play Crazy Comets on my C64. The magic starfield seemed almost impossible to code for a 14 year old and the music by Rob Hubbard totally blew me away. I decided to code a pico8 remake of it together with my 6 year old daughter in order to show her how to make games. We had a fantastic time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://deurell.github.io/crazy_intro.gif&#34; alt=&#34;crazy comets intro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pico8 has the simplicity needed in order to show how everything fits together. Graphics, code, music and effects. You can have a live discussion about game development while coding and showing how things are made. In my ordinary job as a C++ game developer everything takes time, sometimes a lot of time. In Lua and pico8 it&amp;rsquo;s refreshingly fast. Like super, blazingly fast. And at the same time it brings the classic C64 feeling of having control. And what can I say. Kids love pixel art. A perfect teaching environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://deurell.github.io/crazy_game.gif&#34; alt=&#34;crazy comets game&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is implemented as a simple state machine with objects handling the ship, comets, star field, camera, particles and missiles. It handles collision detection with classic AABB bounding boxes and I&amp;rsquo;ll come back to some of the implementation in a future blog post. The game has a whopping total size of 11K. &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download the game with all source code as a cartridge here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://deurell.github.io/cart.p8.png&#34; alt=&#34;cartridge&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or play the game in a web browser by following the following link.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lexaloffle.com/bbs/?tid=32886&#34;&gt;https://lexaloffle.com/bbs/?tid=32886&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>